<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Design on The Quiescent Current</title>
    <link>https://quiescent.us/tags/design/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Design on The Quiescent Current</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>©2022 Jeremy Wright</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://quiescent.us/tags/design/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Design by Refinement: Sorting by Refinement</title>
      <link>https://quiescent.us/2021/12/rsd-sorting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quiescent.us/2021/12/rsd-sorting/</guid>
      <description>In the last posts we&amp;rsquo;ve been studying refinement, and how to utilize refinement into a methodical approach to describe a system and a proposed solutions. Now let&amp;rsquo;s apply it to a simple example, sorting.
This post has a paring with a video
Designing Sorting This article is intended to be paired with it&amp;rsquo;s accompanying video.
Before we begin, let&amp;rsquo;s think about what we want to accomplish:
We want to express the essence of sorting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Design by Refinement: TDD is not Design</title>
      <link>https://quiescent.us/2021/12/rsd-sorting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quiescent.us/2021/12/rsd-sorting/</guid>
      <description>American Sign Language has this beautiful word roughly translated to blur or smear. It means to blur details of a situation in order to see some greater value. It&amp;rsquo;s similar to the idea of not seeing the forest for the trees&amp;hellip; in order to see the forest, the bigger picture, you need to blur the details.
In principle Test Driven Development (TDD1) is an implementation technique. TDD promises to help it&amp;rsquo;s practitioners build the described design, and not overbuild.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The World Is Not Incremental</title>
      <link>https://quiescent.us/2021/03/not-incremental/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2021 15:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quiescent.us/2021/03/not-incremental/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been struggling to understand the stress the TLA⁺ community is putting on the presence of &lt;em&gt;math&lt;/em&gt; in the  specifications.
Namely, that specifications are not programming, and the math simplifies, by abstraction, the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What exactly is being simplified by using math, instead of &amp;ldquo;programming&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During TLA⁺ study group this week, we discussed at least 1 aspect that applying math simplifies the description of our systems $$\rightarrow$$ The number of states.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Importance of System Design</title>
      <link>https://quiescent.us/2012/07/the-importance-of-system-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jul 2012 17:00:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quiescent.us/2012/07/the-importance-of-system-design/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For the small programs we tend to implement as part of a semester project, or the simple &amp;ldquo;one-off/get-it-done&amp;rdquo; programs at work, system design rarely plays a part. However, even in the smallest problems a top-level system design is critical for consistency and ease of use. Class components, regardless of how precise and accurate they are in their own internal design, if they aren&amp;rsquo;t externally consistent with other objects, the system will be brittle, and difficult to use.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
