<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>soft-skills on The Quiescent Current</title>
    <link>https://quiescent.us/tags/soft-skills/</link>
    <description>Recent content in soft-skills on The Quiescent Current</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>©2022 Jeremy Wright</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Jun 2022 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://quiescent.us/tags/soft-skills/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>My personal PKM | How I surface linear and non-linear thinking</title>
      <link>https://quiescent.us/2022/06/think-external/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jun 2022 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quiescent.us/2022/06/think-external/</guid>
      <description>My biggest success on YouTube is How to write a thesis 10 minutes at a time. In that video I describe an abbreviated flow targeted toward getting students to write more, and take advantage of writing as a tool to organize thinking and make compounded progress on their projects. This video however, is just a taste of my overall knowledge management process, and even more than PKM (Personal Knowledge Management) how I manage myself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My bulletjournal inspired tactical todo list</title>
      <link>https://quiescent.us/2022/06/tactical-todo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jun 2022 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quiescent.us/2022/06/tactical-todo/</guid>
      <description>Bullet journaling (Bujo) is an incredible organization tool. If you haven&amp;rsquo;t tried it, check out the original (non-art) form. It&amp;rsquo;s terse, concise, and for my and a lot of people, unreasonably effective. After several years of bullet journals however I was left with a stack of journals, full of unsurfacable interestingness. Many ideas are bound in the pages, but are locked there among many pages of chaff. The signal to noise ratio of the pages is quite low, so it&amp;rsquo;s not a reasonable use of my time to go through and pull out the ideas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Listen | My soft-skills superpower</title>
      <link>https://quiescent.us/2022/06/listen-with-a-pen/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jun 2022 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quiescent.us/2022/06/listen-with-a-pen/</guid>
      <description>Rule 1: Never Interrupt. Be Patient.
Rule 2: Tolerate interruption with grace.
Imagine for a moment you are having a lively discussion with a work colleague. In the middle of your colleague&amp;rsquo;s thought you have an epiphany. Brilliant! Your brain&amp;rsquo;s auto-associative memory is doing it&amp;rsquo;s job! You are surfacing knowledge relevant to the task at hand, and likely it was your colleague&amp;rsquo;s particular phrasing that helped trigger that association. Huah, Teamwork!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
