<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Writing on The Quiescent Current</title>
    <link>https://quiescent.us/tags/writing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Writing on The Quiescent Current</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>©2022 Jeremy Wright</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://quiescent.us/tags/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Recasting how I blog</title>
      <link>https://quiescent.us/2015/06/converting-to-static-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quiescent.us/2015/06/converting-to-static-blog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I wrote my first article for codestrokes in February 2011 - right as I was
accepted to graduate school. My goal was to improve my writing in preparation
for writing a thesis. While through grad school I started with more
traditional writing tool. I started to learn to write, and I found my writing
style: Simplicity.  I started writing with a big fancy word processor.
I blogged with a massive database backed blogging engine. By the time
I finished my thesis, I was writing in vim. I used a makefile to check
spelling and check for simple grammatical rules. The process was much simpler
to manage. This motivated me to convert my blog to a static site. This post
describes my process on simplifying my writing process.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Artifical Intelligence Impact on Medicine</title>
      <link>https://quiescent.us/2013/08/artifical-intelligence-impact-on-medicine/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2013 20:16:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quiescent.us/2013/08/artifical-intelligence-impact-on-medicine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dr. Andrew Weil of the Arizona Center for Integrative Medicine states, “If we can make the correct diagnosis, the healing can begin. If we can’t, both our personal health and our economy are doomed. [1]” Accurate, traceable, and informed diagnosis are paramount to the health of patients. Medicine, within the United States, is an enormous $2.5 Trillion opportunity and with the proliferation of research over many decades new medical findings are being published than could ever be grokked, unassisted, by a doctor [2]. Current advances in data mining have moved to alleviate the shear volume of information available to doctors. Medical data mining offers doctors the tools to distinguish anomalies from trending epidemics; the tools to make evidence based decisions, ultimately leading to more personalized medicine [2].&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Latex Walkthrough</title>
      <link>https://quiescent.us/2013/03/latex-walkthrough/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2013 18:25:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quiescent.us/2013/03/latex-walkthrough/</guid>
      <description>Latex Walkthrough from Jeremy Wright on Vimeo.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Being Truely Productive</title>
      <link>https://quiescent.us/2011/06/being-truely-productive/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2011 18:59:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quiescent.us/2011/06/being-truely-productive/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Productivity is an elusive mistress.  I approach productivity much like any design problem. I lay out my requirements, and I iterate until I am happy with the outcome. Over the last few years I have spent a lot time laying out my design process.  Along the way I found a number of tools that were helpful.  This is my personal process and while I think it&amp;rsquo;s a great process.  It&amp;rsquo;s important to refactor for yourself. The key to my productivity is consistency. I work well with a defined workflow. Lastly, interruptions are a certainty, so one must find a way to make context switches less disruptive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Try to setup natural stopping points in your process. You will be interrupted so make context switches cheap.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consistency &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; my process, and tools help me deal with strict and dynamic constraints.  I use a number of tools help me be productive, yet consistency is the most powerful function for me.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
