<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Property Driven Design on Code Strokes</title>
    <link>http://www.codestrokes.com/categories/property-driven-design/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Property Driven Design on Code Strokes</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.codestrokes.com/categories/property-driven-design/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Property Driven Design: MinMax</title>
      <link>http://www.codestrokes.com/2015/07/property_driven_design_minmax/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.codestrokes.com/2015/07/property_driven_design_minmax/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I wrote an article on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.codestrokes.com/2014/09/property-testing-in-c/&#34;&gt;Property Testing&lt;/a&gt;
about a year ago. Isocpp.org even &lt;a href=&#34;https://isocpp.org/blog/2014/12/property-testing&#34;&gt;linked to
it&lt;/a&gt; which was pretty cool.
Recently, I uncovered a fantastic talk by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=shngiiBfD80&#34;&gt;Jessica Kerr about property
testing&lt;/a&gt;. Kerr&amp;rsquo;s talk
reinvigorated my languid research effort toward generated testing. Kerr
presented the idea (novel to me) that properties aren&amp;rsquo;t rigid. Properties
don&amp;rsquo;t need to exclude all possible incorrect results for a given function.
Properties simply must &lt;em&gt;reduce the size&lt;/em&gt; of the incorrect space. This may seem
like semantics, but it is easier to exclude a wild-ass-guess that verify it is correct.
Additionally, some domains may not have a solidly defined answer,a nd the
result my be probabilistic in nature. This post will focus on deterministic
problems for the moment, but realize that property testing is vastly more
general than mundane example testing. How properties reduce the size of the
problem space makes me imagine this Figure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.codestrokes.com/img/Properties_solution_space.png&#34; alt=&#34;sometimes_code_gives_you_a_wtf&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following Kerr&amp;rsquo;s references, I found a set of projects from a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.ou.edu/~rlpage/SEcollab/20projects/&#34;&gt;predicate-logic
course&lt;/a&gt;. This course
provides 20 separate projects excellently cast for a property-driven-design
tutorial. These projects are unique since besides the typical requirements
they enumerate the predicate functions each requirement typifies. Predicate
functions are to a predicate-logician as properties are to a computer
scientist. These enumerated properties (predicates) clarified
many points I misunderstood about property testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post will step through the design of the first project
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.ou.edu/~rlpage/SEcollab/20projects/minmax.htm&#34;&gt;minmax&lt;/a&gt; using
C++. My primary goal for this article is to address a concern raised by
a colleague, &amp;ldquo;Does pulling in more complexity &amp;mdash; a fancy test
generator &amp;mdash; actually increase quality?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/JeremyLWright/property_driven_design/tree/master/01_minmax&#34;&gt;Code for this article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/JeremyLWright/JeremyLWright.github.io/commits/content/content/posts/2015-07-05-property_driven_design_minmax.markdown&#34;&gt;Revision Log for this article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her presentation, Kerr stated, &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;what is this answer? I don&amp;rsquo;t know but
I can put a box around it!&amp;rdquo; This jestful statement is quite
inspired. Example tests &amp;mdash; the test typically used in unit tests (the FPGA/ASIC
guys call these Directed Tests) &amp;mdash; draw individual points within the
correct region of the solution space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are paradigms, e.g., structured testing using McCabe
complexity, for selecting effective points within this solution space,
 but in the end you are still drawing points. Properties on the
other hand draw boxes around the solution space. Notice that the properties
may include incorrect solutions. While this may seem as a defect to
property driven design, it is precisely this simplification that makes
properties resilient to refactoring and maintenance cycles. While still
providing value by excluding out of bounds results. This resilience is draws
from PDD&amp;rsquo;s lineage as a black-box testing method. Conversely, structured
testing is a whitebox method that looks as what test data will
induce 100% block coverage. As the code changes over time, the
predicates and conditionals change which intern influence the code coverage. In
a sense the points in the correct solution place are always moving around. The
Example based tests are tightly coupled to the implementation they are
attempting to verify. Properties however operate at a higher level of
abstraction. Properties allow one to say &amp;ldquo;solutions of &lt;em&gt;approximately this
form&lt;/em&gt; are likely correct.&amp;rdquo; Properties then may make successively tighter bounds
around the solution space to constraint the design. Its a powerful
technique that I increasingly enjoy in my design work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;implementing-minmax-with-properties:50cf44a3d7a8ca6a3d0b114540b5d3c2&#34;&gt;Implementing MinMax with Properties&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;prerequisites:50cf44a3d7a8ca6a3d0b114540b5d3c2&#34;&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;em&gt;measure&lt;/em&gt; used in this problem statement means as
the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stepanovpapers.com/gcd.pdf&#34;&gt;ancient Greeks meant it&lt;/a&gt;: a line segment which
describes an integer number of divisions of another line segment. Today we might use
the word greatest common divisor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-maximum-function:50cf44a3d7a8ca6a3d0b114540b5d3c2&#34;&gt;The maximum function&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inspired by test-driven-design we&amp;rsquo;ll start by defining a property for our
maximum function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define a function, &lt;em&gt;maximum&lt;/em&gt;, that delivers the largest value in a non-empty list of rational numbers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/thejohnfreeman/autocheck&#34;&gt;autocheck library&lt;/a&gt; we can express this requirement as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-cpp&#34;&gt;struct prop_max_element_t
{
	template&amp;lt;
		typename SinglePassRange&amp;gt;
	bool operator()(const SinglePassRange&amp;amp; xs)
	{
		auto ref_max = std::max_element(std::cbegin(xs), std::cend(xs));
		const auto test_max = minmax::maximum(xs);
		return *ref_max == test_max;
	}
	
};

TEST(minmax, maximum_prop)
{
	autocheck::gtest_reporter rep;

	auto arbitrary = 
		autocheck::discard_if([](const std::vector&amp;lt;size_t&amp;gt;&amp;amp; xs) -&amp;gt; bool { return xs.size() == 0; },
		autocheck::make_arbitrary&amp;lt;std::vector&amp;lt;size_t&amp;gt;&amp;gt;());
		
	autocheck::check&amp;lt;std::vector&amp;lt;size_t&amp;gt;&amp;gt;(
			prop_max_element_t(),
			100,
			arbitrary,
			rep);
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets breakdown the definition of the arbitrary generator:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-cpp&#34;&gt;	auto arbitrary = 
		autocheck::discard_if([](const std::vector&amp;lt;size_t&amp;gt;&amp;amp; xs) -&amp;gt; bool { return xs.size() == 0; },
		autocheck::make_arbitrary&amp;lt;std::vector&amp;lt;size_t&amp;gt;&amp;gt;());
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The signature of an arbitrary generator is best read bottom to top.  The first
step generates a random vector of random length. The line above it throws away
vectors who&amp;rsquo;s size is equal to zero. We will see later how to generate data
that meets our requirements, but sometimes its easier to just throw away some
data rather than try to generate only valid data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this property we can test our stub function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-cpp&#34;&gt;namespace minmax
{

template &amp;lt;typename SinglePassRange&amp;gt;
typename SinglePassRange::value_type maximum(const SinglePassRange&amp;amp; range)
{
	return 0; //Stubbed method
}
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This generates a failed output as we expected&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;[ RUN      ] minmax.maximum_prop
d:\property_driven_design\build\thirdparty\src\autocheck\include\autocheck\reporter.hpp(91): error: Value of: AUTOCHECK_SUCCESS
  Actual: false
Expected: true
Falsifiable, after 3 tests:
([2, 0])

[  FAILED  ] minmax.maximum_prop (3 ms)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we are confident the test machinery is working, we can remove our
stub implementation and provide a (hopefully correct) definition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-cpp&#34;&gt;namespace minmax
{
template &amp;lt;typename SinglePassRange&amp;gt;
typename SinglePassRange::value_type maximum(const SinglePassRange&amp;amp; range)
{
	return *std::max_element(
			std::begin(range),
			std::end(range));
}
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will no re-run our test to verify the implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;[ RUN      ] minmax.maximum_prop
OK, passed 100 tests.
[       OK ] minmax.maximum_prop (14 ms)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This demonstrates another useful property of properties :-). The data passing
through our property is randomly generated, ergo each time the test runs we
execute different tests. Typing &lt;em&gt;make test&lt;/em&gt; multiple times is actually useful, not just something you do to procrastinate at 4:45pm when you&amp;rsquo;ve found
a new bug.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also there is something viscerally satisfying about writing a single property
and seeing 100 tests passing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-compile-time-property:50cf44a3d7a8ca6a3d0b114540b5d3c2&#34;&gt;A compile-time property&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we can verify the property given to us in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.ou.edu/~rlpage/SEcollab/20projects/minmax.htm&#34;&gt;problem statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If xs is a non-empty true-list of rational numbers, then (maximum xs) is a rational number.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since C++ is a statically typed language this property may appear to be self
evident. However this demonstrates another benefit of property driven design.
We can document that we intend to only work with rational numbers. Then since
C++ is statically type we can validate the property statically, and any
maintenance programmer will fail to compile without modifying the test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can express this property as so&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-cpp&#34;&gt;struct prop_maximum_should_give_rational_number_t
{
	template&amp;lt;typename SinglePassRange&amp;gt;
	bool operator()(const SinglePassRange&amp;amp; xs)
	{
		static_assert(std::is_integral&amp;lt;decltype(minmax::maximum(xs))&amp;gt;::value, &amp;quot;Maximum only works on rational numbers.&amp;quot;);
		return std::is_integral&amp;lt;decltype(minmax::maximum(xs))&amp;gt;::value;
	}
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shows another pattern of testing I picked up from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sDMngNP7pOw&#34;&gt;Bruce Tate&lt;/a&gt;, tests should be named as a should-statement. This property here says: My property for maximum &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; give rational numbers. If this is ever falsified our test the static_assert() will fail compilation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can add another property that demonstrates the blackbox nature of property
testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#50;. The value (maximum xs) occurs in the list xs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Properties as basic as this seem silly at first, but they serve a very useful
purpose. Recall the poorly drawn graphic from above. We are searching for bugs
in our program by defining bounds around the solution space. This property
states something very profound about our function. The output of our function
is dependent on the input. This trends the function toward referential
transparency. At a more basic level though, this might be a property one
starts with. Notice that if we implemented this property first, with our stub
function in place, our random generator would have falsified it easily with
any list where 0 was not a member.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can express this property with autocheck as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-cpp&#34;&gt;struct prop_maximum_should_return_a_value_from_the_list_t
{
	template &amp;lt;typename SinglePassRange&amp;gt;
	bool operator()(const SinglePassRange&amp;amp; xs)
	{
		const auto m = minmax::maximum(xs);
		const auto is_present = std::find(
				std::begin(xs),
				std::end(xs),
				m);
		return is_present != std::end(xs);
	}
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, if minmax::maximum returns some value m, that value must be
present in the list.  Notice again that m may be the minimum value in the
list. This property isn&amp;rsquo;t checking for the complete correctness of the
function. It is testing one small aspect of the function&amp;rsquo;s possible solution
space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we can move on to our next function, &lt;em&gt;minimum_pair&lt;/em&gt;, which we can
implement with a stub to always return the first element:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-cpp&#34;&gt;template &amp;lt;typename SinglePassRange&amp;gt;
measure_pair_t minimum_pair(const SinglePassRange&amp;amp; xs)
{
	return *std::begin(xs);
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To property test this function we&amp;rsquo;ll need to teach autocheck how to generate
a &lt;em&gt;measure_pair_t&lt;/em&gt;. We do this by specializing the generator function in the
autocheck namespace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;generating-a-custom-data-type:50cf44a3d7a8ca6a3d0b114540b5d3c2&#34;&gt;Generating a custom data type&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-cpp&#34;&gt;namespace autocheck
{

//Tell autocheck how to generate a measure_pair_t
template &amp;lt;&amp;gt;
class generator&amp;lt;minmax::measure_pair_t&amp;gt;
{
	public:
	using result_type = minmax::measure_pair_t;

	result_type operator()()
	{
		return this-&amp;gt;operator()(0);
	}

	result_type operator()(size_t size)
	{
		auto rational_gen = generator&amp;lt;std::size_t&amp;gt;();
		return std::make_pair(rational_gen(size), rational_gen(size));
	}
};

//Tell autocheck how to display a measure_pair_t
std::ostream&amp;amp; operator&amp;lt;&amp;lt;(std::ostream&amp;amp; os, const minmax::measure_pair_t&amp;amp; p)
{
	os &amp;lt;&amp;lt; &amp;quot;{&amp;quot; &amp;lt;&amp;lt; p.first &amp;lt;&amp;lt; &amp;quot;, &amp;quot; &amp;lt;&amp;lt; p.second &amp;lt;&amp;lt; &amp;quot;}&amp;quot;;
	return os;
}
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;broken-test-code:50cf44a3d7a8ca6a3d0b114540b5d3c2&#34;&gt;Broken Test Code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now autocheck can generate and display our specific type. Setup a property to
check.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#52;. If xs is a non-empty true-list of measure pairs, then (minimum-pair xs) is a measure-pair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To express this property we must first have a definition of a measure pair
(We&amp;rsquo;ll see how this definition is not quite correct, but our properties will
sus that out quite quickly):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-cpp&#34;&gt;using measure_pair_t = std::pair&amp;lt;std::size_t, std::size_t&amp;gt;;

///Provided definition: measure pair: a two-element list whose first element, a rational number, is the measure of its other element
bool is_measure_pair(const measure_pair_t&amp;amp; x)
{
	//A measure pair is a two element list, who&#39;s first element (a rational
	//number), is the measure of its other element
	const auto first_element_is_rational = std::is_integral&amp;lt;decltype(x.first)&amp;gt;::value;

	const auto other_element_is_measure_of_first = 
		//To be a measure the first value must be less-than the second.
		(x.first &amp;lt; x.second)
		//And the second element must evenly divide the first element.
		&amp;amp;&amp;amp; (x.second % x.first == 0);
	return first_element_is_rational
		&amp;amp;&amp;amp; other_element_is_measure_of_first;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And our property to check that the return value from minimum pair should meet
the definition of a measure pair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-cpp&#34;&gt;struct prop_minimum_pair_should_return_a_measure_pair_t
{
	bool operator()(const std::vector&amp;lt;minmax::measure_pair_t&amp;gt;&amp;amp; xs) const
	{
		using namespace minmax;
		const auto test_pair = minimum_pair(xs);
		return is_measure_pair(test_pair);
	}
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Executing this gives us, as expected due to our stub, a falsifiable case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;[ RUN      ] MinMaxFixture.prop_minimum_pair_should_return_a_measure_pair
unknown file: error: SEH exception with code 0xc0000094 thrown in the test body.

[  FAILED  ] MinMaxFixture.prop_minimum_pair_should_return_a_measure_pair (1 ms)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Error 0xc0000094 is a divide by zero. Ah! Good catch autocheck. I know
I personally would not have exercised this using a directed test. This is
another strength of random testing. The random generators are not biased with
programmer intuition. Our requirements state that a measure-pair is always
non-zero so we will update the generator to exclude zero values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-cpp&#34;&gt;namespace autocheck
{
template &amp;lt;&amp;gt;
class generator&amp;lt;minmax::measure_pair_t&amp;gt;
{
	public:
	using result_type = minmax::measure_pair_t;

	result_type operator()()
	{
		return this-&amp;gt;operator()(0);
	}

	result_type operator()(const size_t size)
	{
		const auto non_zero_gen = [size]()
		{
			auto rational_gen = generator&amp;lt;std::size_t&amp;gt;();
			auto temp = rational_gen(size);
			if(temp == 0) //Skip over zero!
				return temp + 1;
			return temp;
		};
		const auto measure = non_zero_gen();
		const auto factor = non_zero_gen();
		return std::make_pair(measure*factor, measure);
	}
};
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now with zero values excluded we&amp;rsquo;ll get a falsifiable test case:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;[ RUN      ] MinMaxFixture.prop_minimum_pair_should_return_a_measure_pair
d:\property_driven_design\build\thirdparty\src\autocheck\include\autocheck\reporter.hpp(91): error: Value of: AUTOCHECK_SUCCESS
  Actual: false
Expected: true
Falsifiable, after 1 tests:
([{1, 1}])

[  FAILED  ] MinMaxFixture.prop_minimum_pair_should_return_a_measure_pair (1 ms)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This test case demonstrates that our understand of the word measure wasn&amp;rsquo;t
quite right when we implemented the &lt;em&gt;is_measure_pair&lt;/em&gt; predicate. A value can
always be a measure of itself, i.e., a number always measures itself one time.
Since our function is still a stub we are still excercising the test
machinery, not the production code yet. One school of thought is
that we are wasting time writing, and rewriting, test code before we&amp;rsquo;ve even
worked on the code we&amp;rsquo;re getting paid to write however, this failing test case is
evidence for a different perspective. The test code is letting us explore the
problem space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine a traditional directed test scenerio. We unknowingly have a limited
understanding of the problem space. We implement some tests. Those tests
reflect our understanding of the problem. We then implement the functions. The
tests pass, all the while we unknowingly provided weak tests for the given
problem domain. Lastly, we inspect the implementation and add some additional
tests to assure 100% code coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this scenerio, we did TDD correctly by writing the tests first. We did our
red/green refactor. We implemented the function. Our tests pass, and we
achieved 100% code coverage. We did all the things we are supposed to do, and
we still delivered a defective function. The problem is that all these steps
happen at the same conceptual level of abstraction. It&amp;rsquo;s a linear prorgession
from our understanding, to writing tests, to writing implementation, to
inspecting coverage. At no point was there some outside force that can
excercise the code beyond our understanding. This is the benefit of
property-driven-design. Randomness will generate test cases you the programmer
didn&amp;rsquo;t think of. You the programmer then need to classify that generated test
case as valid input or invalid input. That is a useful! It expands your own
understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Hughes &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FnjutUoNSmg&#34;&gt;put it
best&lt;/a&gt; when he state that property
testing is about comparing the specification to the code. The properties
encode the specification. The code does what it does. When the checker finds
a discrepancy it is the engineer&amp;rsquo;s job to find where the defect lies. This is
very powerful. We, the engineer, aren&amp;rsquo;t relegated to imagining test data for
our functions what will make it blow up. We simply describe concepts
(properties) of what we believe the specification is telling us to do. Then we
implement the code. If the two match then we the code probably matches the
specification. Its raises our level of thinking out of individual numbers, and
code paths to more abstract thinking, which is something humans do best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fixing-our-property:50cf44a3d7a8ca6a3d0b114540b5d3c2&#34;&gt;Fixing our property&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is is that our definition doesn&amp;rsquo;t include self-measures. We can
adjust it easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-cpp&#34;&gt;bool is_measure_pair(const measure_pair_t&amp;amp; x)
{
	//A measure pair is a two element list, who&#39;s first element (a rational
	//number), is the measure of its other element
	const auto first_element_is_rational = std::is_integral&amp;lt;decltype(x.first)&amp;gt;::value;

	const auto other_element_is_measure_of_first = 
		//To be a measure the first value must be equal-to or less-than the second.
		(x.first == x.second) ||
		((x.first &amp;lt; x.second )
		//And the second element must evenly divide the first element.
		&amp;amp;&amp;amp; (x.second % x.first == 0));
	return first_element_is_rational
		&amp;amp;&amp;amp; other_element_is_measure_of_first;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Executing this generates a new failing case:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;[ RUN      ] MinMaxFixture.prop_minimum_pair_should_return_a_measure_pair
d:\property_driven_design\build\thirdparty\src\autocheck\include\autocheck\repor
ter.hpp(91): error: Value of: AUTOCHECK_SUCCESS
  Actual: false
Expected: true
Falsifiable, after 3 tests:
([{2, 1}, {2, 2}])

[  FAILED  ] MinMaxFixture.prop_minimum_pair_should_return_a_measure_pair (1 ms)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can run it again to see if we get a different case:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;[ RUN      ] MinMaxFixture.prop_minimum_pair_should_return_a_measure_pair
d:\property_driven_design\build\thirdparty\src\autocheck\include\autocheck\reporter.hpp(91): error: Value of: AUTOCHECK_SUCCESS
  Actual: false
Expected: true
Falsifiable, after 7 tests:
([{4, 1}, {4, 2}, {2, 2}, {1, 1}])

[  FAILED  ] MinMaxFixture.prop_minimum_pair_should_return_a_measure_pair (1 ms)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is awesome! Our failing test case is bigger now. Again to quote John
Hughes, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zi0rHwfiX1Q&#34;&gt;This is progress! We are now passing for lists of size 1!&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; Our function is still implemented as a stub, so we can have some confidence that our test code is behaving properly. Let&amp;rsquo;s implement our minimum_pair function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-cpp&#34;&gt;template &amp;lt;typename SinglePassRange&amp;gt;
measure_pair_t minimum_pair(const SinglePassRange&amp;amp; xs)
{
	return *std::min_element(
			std::begin(xs),
			std::end(xs),
			::minmax::operator&amp;lt;);
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Executing our test code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;D:\property_driven_design\build&amp;gt;01_minmax
Running main() from gtest_main.cc
[==========] Running 7 tests from 3 test cases.
[----------] Global test environment set-up.
[----------] 1 test from minmax
[ RUN      ] minmax.maximum_directed
[       OK ] minmax.maximum_directed (0 ms)
[----------] 1 test from minmax (1 ms total)

[----------] 5 tests from MinMaxFixture
[ RUN      ] MinMaxFixture.prop_maximum_should_give_greatest_value
OK, passed 100 tests.
[       OK ] MinMaxFixture.prop_maximum_should_give_greatest_value (13 ms)
[ RUN      ] MinMaxFixture.prop_maximum_should_give_rational_number
OK, passed 100 tests.
[       OK ] MinMaxFixture.prop_maximum_should_give_rational_number (11 ms)
[ RUN      ] MinMaxFixture.prop_maximum_should_return_a_value_from_the_list
OK, passed 100 tests (2% trivial).
10% 10, odd-length.
10% 20, even-length.
10% 30, odd-length.
10% 40, even-length.
10% 50, odd-length.
10% 60, even-length.
10% 70, odd-length.
10% 80, even-length.
10% 90, odd-length.
9% 0, even-length.
[       OK ] MinMaxFixture.prop_maximum_should_return_a_value_from_the_list (24 ms)
[ RUN      ] MinMaxFixture.prop_minimum_pair_should_return_a_measure_pair
OK, passed 100 tests.
[       OK ] MinMaxFixture.prop_minimum_pair_should_return_a_measure_pair (20 ms)
[ RUN      ] MinMaxFixture.prop_minimum_pair_should_return_the_smallest_pair
OK, passed 100 tests.
[       OK ] MinMaxFixture.prop_minimum_pair_should_return_the_smallest_pair (23 ms)
[----------] 5 tests from MinMaxFixture (92 ms total)

[----------] 1 test from MinMaxDirected
[ RUN      ] MinMaxDirected.directed_minimum_pair_shouls_return_a_measure_pair
[       OK ] MinMaxDirected.directed_minimum_pair_shouls_return_a_measure_pair (0 ms)
[----------] 1 test from MinMaxDirected (0 ms total)

[----------] Global test environment tear-down
[==========] 7 tests from 3 test cases ran. (96 ms total)
[  PASSED  ] 7 tests.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running this multiple times generates no failing test cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;conclusion:50cf44a3d7a8ca6a3d0b114540b5d3c2&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a few real-world metrics. I wrote this code in 3 hours. The
requirements were relatively simple, but I suspect that using example tests
would have resulted in a similar completion time. Additionally, I suspect, my
directed tests would have found more defects near the end of my development
rather than the beginning. I felt this affect as an acceleration. I found feel
as I closed each property that I had fewer defects in the code I previously
thought was done. This is a big confidence booster in my opinion.
Additionally, another pattern I learned from John Hughes, that I didn&amp;rsquo;t
explicitly describe here but you can see in the code, save failed tests.
A failing test is gold! When the random generator uncovers something
interesting save it as a directed test. Then fix the failure and leave the
directed test behind. It will be a reminder of a corner case you missed. Plus
some developers like to see examples tests, even random ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post I walked through a property-driven-design approach to a simple
numerical problem. In intended to show something more interesting that the
&lt;em&gt;reverse(reverse(list)) == list&lt;/em&gt; example, and something less contrived than my
previous post on property testing. I look forward to any feedback on this
post.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>