<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tla&#43; on The Quiescent Current</title>
    <link>https://quiescent.us/languages/tla&#43;/</link>
    <description>Recent content in tla&#43; on The Quiescent Current</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>©2022 Jeremy Wright</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://quiescent.us/languages/tla+/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Design by Refinement: Sorting by Refinement</title>
      <link>https://quiescent.us/2021/12/rsd-sorting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quiescent.us/2021/12/rsd-sorting/</guid>
      <description>In the last posts we&amp;rsquo;ve been studying refinement, and how to utilize refinement into a methodical approach to describe a system and a proposed solutions. Now let&amp;rsquo;s apply it to a simple example, sorting.
This post has a paring with a video
Designing Sorting This article is intended to be paired with it&amp;rsquo;s accompanying video.
Before we begin, let&amp;rsquo;s think about what we want to accomplish:
We want to express the essence of sorting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Design by Refinement: TDD is not Design</title>
      <link>https://quiescent.us/2021/12/rsd-sorting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quiescent.us/2021/12/rsd-sorting/</guid>
      <description>American Sign Language has this beautiful word roughly translated to blur or smear. It means to blur details of a situation in order to see some greater value. It&amp;rsquo;s similar to the idea of not seeing the forest for the trees&amp;hellip; in order to see the forest, the bigger picture, you need to blur the details.
In principle Test Driven Development (TDD1) is an implementation technique. TDD promises to help it&amp;rsquo;s practitioners build the described design, and not overbuild.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>21st Century Proof :: Structure makes it possible, hard work makes it probable</title>
      <link>https://quiescent.us/2021/09/twenty-first-century-proof/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Sep 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quiescent.us/2021/09/twenty-first-century-proof/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A new way of expressing: &amp;ldquo;work smarter not harder&amp;rdquo; -&amp;gt; Structure makes it possible, hard work makes it probable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Detail can obscure the big picture. Structure can help, if it allows for a personalized, or tunable about of illumination.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A proof is not easy if we must read the entire proof to understand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lamport.azurewebsites.net/pubs/proof.pdf&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My TLA&#43; Saga</title>
      <link>https://quiescent.us/2021/09/my-tla-saga/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quiescent.us/2021/09/my-tla-saga/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning together is more fun, and you may not be as self-taught as you believe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The stories we tell ourselves deeply impact our ability (or inability) to grow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The more you learn, the more challenging the material becomes to continue growing. (a.k.a. Duh, but it took me time to realize it, regardless)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The World Is Not Incremental</title>
      <link>https://quiescent.us/2021/03/not-incremental/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2021 15:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quiescent.us/2021/03/not-incremental/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been struggling to understand the stress the TLA⁺ community is putting on the presence of &lt;em&gt;math&lt;/em&gt; in the  specifications.
Namely, that specifications are not programming, and the math simplifies, by abstraction, the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What exactly is being simplified by using math, instead of &amp;ldquo;programming&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During TLA⁺ study group this week, we discussed at least 1 aspect that applying math simplifies the description of our systems $$\rightarrow$$ The number of states.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
