<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>cracking on Quiescent Engineering, LLC.</title>
    <link>/tags/cracking/</link>
    <description>Recent content in cracking on Quiescent Engineering, LLC.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>©2020 Jeremy Wright</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2013 21:58:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/tags/cracking/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Linux User&#39;s Group CTF 2013</title>
      <link>/2013/09/linux-users-group-ctf-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2013 21:58:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/linux-users-group-ctf-2013/</guid>
      <description>This past weekend we held another capture the flag event at the Arizona State University&amp;rsquo;s Linux User&amp;rsquo;s Group. It had more of a system admin focus than security cracking exploits, but it was fun an nontheless a diverse learning experience for all those involved. However, almost immediately, I realized the number one rule in CTF, nothing is off limits!
The game was organized into two parts, a game server which collected the the scores and displayed the point totals of all teams in real-time, and the virtual servers (hosted on Amazon EC2) which contained the actual games.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Capture the Flag - Running a Hacking Competition</title>
      <link>/2012/04/capture-the-flag-running-a-hacking-competition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2012 02:38:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/capture-the-flag-running-a-hacking-competition/</guid>
      <description>Black-Hat hacking in an controlled environment, like this, is an important skill for software developers. The Art of War describes knowing one&amp;rsquo;s enemy, and with the prevalence of internet-enabled applications today, it has never been more critical to know how the &amp;ldquo;enemy&amp;rdquo; can take down a system. While capture-the-flag is a fun, and exciting intellectual game, it is serious training for software engineers of all types, and skill levels. I recently setup a small capture the flag event for the Arizona Linux User&amp;rsquo;s Group, and it was very fun.</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
