<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>book on The Quiescent Current</title>
    <link>https://quiescent.us/tags/book/</link>
    <description>Recent content in book on The Quiescent Current</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>©2022 Jeremy Wright</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://quiescent.us/tags/book/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Design by Refinement: Sorting by Refinement</title>
      <link>https://quiescent.us/2021/12/rsd-sorting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quiescent.us/2021/12/rsd-sorting/</guid>
      <description>In the last posts we&amp;rsquo;ve been studying refinement, and how to utilize refinement into a methodical approach to describe a system and a proposed solutions. Now let&amp;rsquo;s apply it to a simple example, sorting.
This post has a paring with a video
Designing Sorting This article is intended to be paired with it&amp;rsquo;s accompanying video.
Before we begin, let&amp;rsquo;s think about what we want to accomplish:
We want to express the essence of sorting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Design by Refinement: TDD is not Design</title>
      <link>https://quiescent.us/2021/12/rsd-sorting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quiescent.us/2021/12/rsd-sorting/</guid>
      <description>American Sign Language has this beautiful word roughly translated to blur or smear. It means to blur details of a situation in order to see some greater value. It&amp;rsquo;s similar to the idea of not seeing the forest for the trees&amp;hellip; in order to see the forest, the bigger picture, you need to blur the details.
In principle Test Driven Development (TDD1) is an implementation technique. TDD promises to help it&amp;rsquo;s practitioners build the described design, and not overbuild.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Write a Thesis</title>
      <link>https://quiescent.us/2013/07/review-how-to-write-a-thesis-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2013 04:48:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quiescent.us/2013/07/review-how-to-write-a-thesis-2/</guid>
      <description>My family purchased this book for me, as a motivator to start thinking about the thesis component of my master&amp;rsquo;s degree. &amp;ldquo;It must be substantial&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; said a colleague of mine. &amp;ldquo;It must be original work&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; Original, substantial, all words that left me with uneasiness about how to start. This book however was an easy read, and gave some very pragmatic advice on how to start, yet the most important quote I drew from the book was, &amp;ldquo;What are the questions in your field?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
