<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Substitution Cipher on Jeremy&#39;s CodeStrokes</title>
    <link>http://www.codestrokes.com/tags/substitution-cipher/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Substitution Cipher on Jeremy&#39;s CodeStrokes</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Creative Commons Share Alike</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2014 08:50:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.codestrokes.com/tags/substitution-cipher/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Massively Intelligent Non-Deterministic Luminating Effortless Super Solver</title>
      <link>http://www.codestrokes.com/2014/02/cracking-subciphercpp/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2014 08:50:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.codestrokes.com/2014/02/cracking-subciphercpp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I worked the title of this article several times before I finally settled on the subtly epic heading you see above. Hopefully this title will funnel people off google into my blog (delicious SEO). I wanted to push the A.I. component of my solution because A.I. is awesome and mysterious, and cool (and can like solve jeopardy). I was quickly disillusioned however. Really, A.I. isn&amp;rsquo;t magic, rather it&amp;rsquo;s just the same thing computers have been doing for a long time: computing. Sadly this realization took several months in an A.I. class before I was sufficiently crestfallen. A.I. patterns including the hill climbing algorithm used here are indeed &amp;ldquo;intelligent&amp;rdquo; but really it a reflecting of the algorithm designer, not the entity executing the algorithm. So I built a substitution cipher solver in C++. It&amp;rsquo;s fast it uses random numbers i.e. non-deterministic, it uses an A.I. algorithm i.e. Intelligent, it uses threads i.e. Massively, it deciphers i.e. luminates the text and it solves super stuff therefore the title is completely justified. I give you my Massively Intelligent Non-Deterministic Luminating Effortless Super Solver (MINDLESS). If none of that interests you then please stick around and follow the side quest of looking for &lt;a href=&#34;http://justenoughcraig.blogspot.com/2014/01/just-say-no-to-passive-aggressive.html&#34;&gt;emotionally charged parenthesis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>